A Guide to the Enniscorthy Collection 1926-1970
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Enniscorthy Collection 1926-1970
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11606
250 items(1 Hollinger box and 1 OS folder)
This collection consists primarily of correspondence, architectural drawings, sketches, plats, designs, news clippings, specifications, abstracts of title, and other papers concerning the historic house and property "Enniscorthy," Albemarle County, Virginia, 1926-1968, compiled by the Kulikowski family during their tenure at the house, ca. 1942-1955. There are also a few items pertaining to an unidentified house belonging to Adam H. Kulikowski in Louisa County, Virginia.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Enniscorthy Collection was given to the University of Virginia Library by Frances Kulikowski, La Jolla, California, on April 1, 2000.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists primarily of correspondence, architectural drawings, sketches, plats, designs, news clippings, specifications, abstracts of title, and other papers concerning the historic house and property Enniscorthy, Albemarle County, Virginia, 1926-1968, compiled by the Kulikowski family during their tenure at the house, ca. 1942-1955. There are also a few items pertaining to an unidentified house belonging to Adam H. Kulikowski in Louisa County, Virginia.
John Coles built the original structure on the tract of land which was called Enniscorthy, after the Coles family ancestral home in Leinster, Wexford County, Ireland. The land had been purchased by the Coles family around 1769 from the holder of the original land grant, Francis Eppes. In 1839 the house, now belonging to Isaac A. Coles (1780-1841), burnt to the ground. In 1850, his widow, Julianna Strickler Rankin Coles built a new brick structure on the site. Her son, Strickler Coles, sold the property to his relative, Tucker Skipwith Coles. Upon his death, the place was inherited by Lelia Coles Bennet (died ca. 1926).
In 1926, the property passed out of the Coles family and was sold to Mr. & Mrs. Albert Morrill, Cincinnati, Ohio. Enniscorthy was purchased in 1942 by Mr. And Mrs. Adam Kulikowski, Chicago, Illinois, who sold the property to Edward M. Keating in 1955.
Oversize items include a blueprint for alterations and additions for a house in Louisa County, Virginia, owned by Mr. A.H. Kulikowski; a blueprint for a cattle guard; a blueprint showing the location of carrara [marble?] and mirrors in a bathroom at Enniscorthy; two plats of the Enniscorthy Farm, Keene, Virginia, with the location of the plantation, pine trees, and hardwood trees noted; and several drawings of rooms, cabinets, drawers, sinks, and other interior drawings, presumably all of Enniscorthy; and a cross ventilation window system.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically.
Partial Contents List
- Abstracts of Title for Enniscorthy of Albert H. & Lily Logan Morrill and of John D. Wheeler, Sr. 1942 & 1955
- Contract for the Sale of Enniscorthy between Adam H. Kulikowski and Edward M. Keating 1955
- Correspondence re the purchase of Enniscorthy by the Kulikowski family and subsequent alterations and additions 1942 Mar-1954
- Correspondence with Floyd E. Johnson re alterations & additions to Enniscorthy 1954
- Drawings and sketches of furniture & interiors at Enniscorthy ca. 1942-1955
- Equipment and livestock on Enniscorthy Farm, including taw returns showing agricultural workers 1938-1955
- Financial & legal papers 1942-1955
- Inspection & Survey Report Property of A.H., Mary T. and Leon Kulikowski known as Enniscorthy 1942 Jun
- Insurance policies 1942-1967
- News clippings re Enniscorthy Farm and other information 1926-1955
- Plats of property, presumably all in Albemarle County, Virginia 1947 & n.d.
- Property brochure & real estate ads featuring Enniscorthy ca. 1942-1968
- Specifications for alterations and additions to a house for Mr. A.H. Kulikowski in Louisa County, Virginia 1942 Mar 7